Hello, welcome everyone. It is October
15th, 2025. We're in active guest stream
122.1
with Andrea Hut who will be presenting
and discussing radical relations,
scaling without hierarchies, models
without me. So if you're watching live,
please write any comments or questions
in the live chat. Otherwise, Andrea,
thank you for joining. Looking forward
to sharing and discussing.
>> Thanks, Daniel. It's really good to be
here. It's sort of last minute, so this
is um very exploratory.
And yeah, I'm Andrea Hyatt, and I'm
going to try and link some ideas kind of
as we go. We'll see. We'll see how it
goes. Um, I just wrote a paper called
radical embodied relation at any scale
and it's coming out of the radical
embodied tradition. I think you've had a
few people on here from that tradition
in the streams. Um, but I'm not going to
spend a lot of time looking deeply at
the paper. Um but I am going to think
about it and relation to active imprints
and also to this other paper which came
out very recently uh with some people in
H Highleberg from some people at the
universities at H Highleberg which is
where I'm at and other places too in
Germany. Uh, a lot of this comes from
my time at Mox Plunk with the Do Lab and
you a lot of these themes are about the
hippocampus and movement and this paper
grid cells accurately track movement
during path integration based navigation
despite switching reference frames is a
really exciting paper. I know the title
might not show that unless you know
about all these things, but they're
moving forward some of the things that I
talk about in my paper in an interesting
way.
So, if I can get the Okay, did that
shift?
Yeah. Um, and feel free to interrupt me
anytime if there's any way to do so.
Uh, you too, Daniel. Because, uh, if I
say something that doesn't make sense
with active inference, I'd love to know.
So, I'm thinking about radical
embodiment meets active inference. I
actually think they're already really
doing a lot of similar things in the way
that I present it in that paper. Of
course, there's a million ways to think
about all of this, but one sort of
obstacle that isn't an obstacle for for
me, but that comes up a lot when I'm
talking about Carl Fston's work or about
other work is this idea of the model
being in the brain. And um Carl and I
had a talk about that on Love and
Philosophy. And that one of the things
that most a lot of people wrote emails
to me about was that models in the
brain. It's and I know it frustrates uh
Carl and others, but I think it's worth
lingering on a little bit here because I
think it's a kind of confusion that we
can really get past and maybe these two
there's a lot of different traditions
actually that I think once we move past
that block uh start to start making a
lot of resonance and that's one reason I
talk about way making which is another
sort of annoying word I know for some
people maybe because it sounds like a
little bit sweet. But what I'm really
trying to do with that is pull back from
all these dualistic ways that we say we
don't take part in anymore in terms of
mental, physical or mind, body or
whatever. Pick your dualism. Um or body
brain or you know mind brain uh but we
still our language is still sort of
pushing us into those which is often
what's happening with this models in the
brain thing. So waym is just kind of
trying to understand all of this action
and this process in a way that we can
assess from different points of view and
it's just trying to present an approach
that gets us out of those routes of the
the binary that we don't always notice
and if you really care about that you
can find other ways other places I've
written about it but this is just coming
out of that a little bit and the way
making is really just an approach it's
not some kind of rigorous thing it's
what I'm trying to do to break us out of
those patterns and then we can assess
different forms of navigability in
different landscapes. So they could be
geographical, conceptual, emotional, ex
etc. But I'm going to focus here on the
hippoc campus which is what I studied
when I was doing my sort of theoretical
neuroscience degree always connected to
philosophy and which I was really
interested in about 10 years ago and I
started working uh on it and a lot of
papers were coming out of Mox Plunk just
beginning then to link what is now sort
of being taken for granted but this idea
of memory and navigation as being
connected in a deep way. Uh, I've had a
lot of talks about that again on Love
and Philosophy. If you really care about
it, you can go there. But here, I just
for the hippocampus, it's the seed of
memory. You've probably heard of it as
connected to memory. When you take the
hippocampus out in these famous cases
like HM, uh, then you can't create new
memories. Again, I'm sort of
generalizing, but that's the basics. And
then you've probably heard of play cells
and grid cells and this brain's GPS,
which is the same part of the brain, but
this is when we're moving through a
landscape, how we're sort of finding our
way. They're literally firing in
relation to how we move. They're super
cool. Like if you look at the um actual
experiments where you can see this real
time activity in the brain and in
relation to the environment, the place
cells, grid cells, and so and so on. Uh,
and then we have this idea of the
cognitive map, which again has a million
different views, but um that connects
back to that model in the head sort of
thing, this map that's in their head.
Um, or we'll get to it, but the
hippocampus as a cognitive map. And none
of these are really wrong or right, but
they're very relative to that structure
of that dualism I was talking about
where we're making choices. So, there's
kind of three iterations I just want to
mention sort of briefly. and um
in the hippocampus literature and
there's a lot in the hippocampus
literature. So this is a very tiny part
of it but important part for this
the memory part one of the most famous
papers 1957
you've probably heard of HM if you've
studied like memory at all the man who
had his hypoc campus removed from
epilepsy and there's this famous paper
with Brendan Milner and Scoville coming
out of this McGill school and I'm going
to generalize it a lot here but from
this work which was a lot of very
interesting amazing work especially
especially kind of setting the way we
think about representations and models
in the brain. Um we kind of started to
think the hypoc campus has to do with
memory because it's linked obviously in
these studies and um it's more you know
it's essential for the explicit memories
and you know once you've formed your
memories you can still have them but you
can't form new ones and there's a lot of
nuance about that too but that's just
one iteration that's really important.
So we started thinking of memory and now
there's these kinds of memory. They're
in the head in different parts of the
brain and so on. And then in the 70s,
John O'Keeffe found these cells that I
was just talking about, play cells,
which fire in relation to a place in the
environment. And this is where this GPS
of the brain idea started, which is a
cartoon version to say it's a GPS. But
again, something super cool is
happening. And you know there's really
something special going on uh in our
body in relation to the environment and
place cells, grid cells, border cells,
head direction cells um in with the New
York downstate guys were finding that
around this time. So there's this whole
beautiful wonderful exciting literature
about the same area of the brain that we
thought was essential for memory and
still is. And for a while people thought
these okay how do we reconcile this?
memory and its navigation and like how
does this go together? And if you look
back at a lot of the papers, uh they're
trying to figure that out and there's
almost two kind of groups
um going and in the late '7s and over
the past 30 years this book the
hippocampus as a cognitive map has
become sort of an orienting force in
certain parts of neuroscience which has
just really spread and into all kinds of
ways. is I mean from the computation to
the cognitive neuroscience which is
thinking of Edvard Tolman's idea of the
cognitive map in the hippocampus. So
then we have this cognitive map. So
that's just the kind of iterations that
we got now thinking about cognitive maps
in brains and and and this thing I
brought up about models and
representations and then what I was
doing in 2000 whatever it was 17 181 19
uh this was a time when a lot of labs
like Tim Baron's lab and the do lab at
Maxplank Tim Barren was is in London
were starting to rethink this connection
between memory and navigation in a
really interesting way and again there's
tons of other people who were doing it
in other papers, but they made some
really important big papers for me where
they started linking this in different
ways and this idea that we think in the
way we navigate or we navigate in the
way we think or or something like that.
Um so for me these papers which I don't
have time to go into completely here but
they started to show that we have this
ongoing process and we're assessing it
from different ways and you can't
reconcile you know like when you're
looking for something that we call
memory you don't reconcile that with
what is happening when you're doing
navigation. However, maybe we can sort
of detach a bit in the way I was talking
about with the waym making and and this
might offer us a way to re-imagine what
we're really talking about with these
cognitive acts like memory and knowledge
and the old way we thought of them and
these physical acts like moving through
a room, finding our way through a city.
Uh so I just find this incredibly
interesting and wonderful and the work
that they were doing then. And my last
paper comes out of that tradition and
it's philosophical though and it's
talking about the hippoc campus a lot
but linking it to um ideas of radical
embodied uh cognition and not only that
but you know mostly that and in the
sense of uh that we don't need to think
about representations or models in the
brain in the way we once thought of
them. Um, and of course, radical
embodied cognitive science, uh, with
like Chimero and everyone is often
thought about as saying there's no such
thing as a representation, but they're
not actually really saying that. Um,
or maybe some people are, but here's the
way I see it, and the way I present it
in that paper is that we can sort of
have our cake and eat it too. There are
representations, but they're not in the
brain. And it has to do with this
assumption I was talking about that we
still talk about looking for them in the
brain even though most people don't
actually think we're going to find
something called a representation that
you can sort of you know find in in the
meat. Um and I hate that word meat and I
can't believe I put it in the title but
I did because well I'll tell you later
why I did. But then we have active
inference which
uh I have no idea what time it is by the
way but so you're going to have to just
tell me. But uh
I think a lot like a lot of the things
that inspire me about active inference
and Carl's work inspire me about all
this other stuff I've been talking
about. So I'm trying to find ways to
talk about this and just the basic ideas
that seem to have entered the atmosphere
from I don't know if this was the first
paper 2009 I just sort of guessed but
maybe it was even earlier but since then
I feel like we've been trying to look
for this unified framework you know
where perception action learning are
thought of in a similar way to what I
was just saying about memory and
navigation in the sense that we're not
separating them in the same way we were
before. So sensing and acting um and how
organisms explore and exploit and
epistemic and pragmatic I I I see a lot
of resonances in that in the way that
I'm trying to talk about memory and
navigation. But again, this is just
exploratory. Uh, but I do think it
relates a lot to this confusion about
models in the brain and the way a lot of
people just turn off from either of
these ideas, radical embodied cognition
or maybe even active inference when they
when they hear that or when they look at
the way that's expressed in certain
ways. But I actually think this is
really exciting that these are doing
something similar. And I feel this
excitement, but I don't know how to
express it really yet. Uh, because I
just started thinking about it. And I'll
try to I'll try to I'm going to unpack
this more in another talk later, but
this is just from today really uh in the
ne the past few days thinking about this
a bit. Um these obstacles that get in
the way and this language and and what
it means and I do think it actually
means means a lot. And an interesting
side note with Lin Nadell who's one of
the people who wrote hippocampus as a
cognitive map. In one of our talks we've
had like five now. I think most of them
are public. He actually starts talking
about active inference or about Carl's
work and um saying that when they were
writing the book they were thinking
about a lot of similar things. They
didn't use the word inference and they
didn't think of it as prediction. Uh but
you know he he brought that up too that
there was some kind of resonance there
that that he felt um
and yeah uh so if we get to this radical
idea this idea that we don't need
representations or that there aren't
representations in the brain for example
um which again is one part of this
tradition which says a lot more than
that but I think it also relates to
ecological ical psychology. I mean,
obviously that's a big part of that
tradition, the radical embodied
cognitive science tradition. And I I
feel that there's a lot of resonances
here with all that I've brought up that
are helping us understand a different
way of un of thinking about cognition
that relates to a lot of work that's
going on in biology such as, you know,
Mike Leaven and Richard Watson and this
cognition first and multiscale. And I
feel ti like tied up within that is
getting out of these habits that we
don't notice we have about dualisms and
binary ways of separating what we're
working on as we're doing the work and
as we're doing the papers. And one big
glaring kind of
thing aspect of that for me is the way
we use neural representation also mental
representation but I'm focusing on
neural representations mostly in the
paper because most neuroscientists as I
said aren't looking for little diagrams
or hieroglyphs as Roman Brea calls it uh
in the brain. However, we write our
papers as if we are and I think that's
causing more trouble than we
I mean a lot of people are trying to
figure this problem out. Obviously,
everyone knows this is causing trouble.
But so, in that paper, I talk about them
as communicative. I basically say we we
have representations obviously, but
they're not to be found. And that we
have to understand that.
This is where it gets tricky for me.
There's a there's a difference between
the way we're assessing a certain
situation and what we're using to do
that and what's actually in whatever it
is that we're looking at as we assess.
So that's what the paper goes into in a
lot of kind of detail. But the reason I
use this meat machines thing is because
Ned Block who was kind enough to let me
sit in on his lectures uh was it last
year? I don't know. Um came out with
this paper. can only meet machines be
conscious recently and I actually think
all these same subjects have a lot to do
with what he's saying in that paper um
and it's a good way to think about it
like that we don't actually have these
models and representations in the body
in that way in that sense uh but that
they're still really there and what I
like a lot about the grid cells during
path integration paper is that it even
goes another step further it's a really
recent paper, but it actually says like,
okay, it's not a GPS in the brain. It's
doing this. Um, and I'm sorry for those
who read the paper that I can't put this
in perfect words yet, but it's there's a
lot of things going on at once uh with
this system in the hippocampus. It's
more constellatory or like a
constellation in my way of saying it.
many dimensions uh at once, not just um
a GPS
at the same time. So, there's a way to
have the models and assessments that are
real and they can be right or wrong and
they can lead to real results, but it
depends on the task and this and the way
you've set everything up and I think we
all know this, but really making it a
foundational part of how we talk about
it is kind of what we're trying to move
towards, I guess. Um Daniel, what time
is it? Do you
>> 22 okay
so I'm just going to go through some
slides which I just helped claude coding
helped me make these so I'm just want to
say that I just basically was saying
what I wanted to try to show with them
and
um so we if we think about the hierarchy
of you know this is higher and lower and
the higher is the reasoning the planning
the remembering and then that's It's all
that stuff of memory and knowledge, I
guess. And then the lower is usually
thought of as the movement, the
sensation, the action, the finding your
way through the city or the room. And I
think those don't really help us
anymore. And the hierarchy way of
thinking about it. And I know I'm not
new saying that. I think all these
traditions I've just expressed are
saying that,
but it's just a good way to look at how
these uh are are connected.
So with the play cells they're not
representing uh
we were thinking of earlier it was
almost like there's a cognitive map in
your head that's you know guiding you or
something but all of this is actually
happening much more in like an
ecological sense or an immediate sense
or an active inference sense actually
and uh this you know where it's where
it's ongoing it's real it's happening
but it's changing all the time in in
many dimensions. So, it's not that
there's one little kind of hieroglyph
that's always happening when you
encounter something, but there's
patterns and regularities that can be
assessed. So, you know, there's these
are just different ways of of thinking
about that. They're more like predictive
dynamics that are bound with movement,
we could say. I I I'm just thinking
about ways words might go across all
these different traditions that I've
just brought up. Um, and in the grid
cells, like in the paper, I didn't go
into it, but the grid cells are kind of
the biggest mystery and the most
wondrous thing in the Moser lab. They're
doing all kind of really cool stuff with
it, too, which I would like to introduce
with this paper cuz I think there's
resonance, but that would be a whole
other talk. But
they have these hexagonal firing
patterns, and it's not like a single
coordinate system. at least as I've read
this paper, it's it's starting to think
about it as like doing multiple
reference frames at once. So, it's
anchoring to different tasks and uh in
that way I express with the GPS this
immediate sort of way that you can see
that the body is
you know synchronizing with its
environment to put it in too general of
a term and you can actually see that and
and you can predict it. you you know you
can watch the rat in the maze and then
you can predict exactly what is going to
fire after you've done that. So there's
this definite regularity and kind of
amazing thing that's happening but it's
happening at multiple levels and it's
not happening in a way that clearly can
be understood as here's the mental and
here's the physical or here's the moving
through the room and here's the moving
through um the memory. It's more about
which one are we looking at, which one
are we assessing, and what are we
assessing about the body relative to
whatever we've, you know, assumed about
that word, whether it's mental or
physical or or whatever.
So, just one way of thinking about it, I
was thinking about like where are
models, where is the model? And I'm
being really sloppy here with the word
representation and model. I know that,
but I think the idea is similar of what
I'm trying to say. Um,
so when you ride a bicycle, where is the
knowledge? Where's the, you know, of
course that's a different kind of
memory. So, I'm again mixing all of
this, but you might say it's like stored
somewhere in your body or in your
cortex. Um, and I could have had a
better example of this, but just the
idea that you're doing something and
you've stored it and you're bringing it
back out and
but what actually is really happening
obviously is that you're coupling with
the bike and with the environment and
that whole process is the memory. So
yeah, you have a memory of what it's
like to be on the bike and move it, but
that's changing as you move through the
landscape depending where you are,
depending what your body is doing that
day. And you might have the same bodily
patterns or the same neural patterns,
but
it's um the riding competence. It's it's
the communication of your body, the
bike, and the environment that is the
pattern that we're going to notice that
continues. And there's a lot of
different ideas about models in the
brain that I I thought I could go into,
but I'm just going to skip that. But
basically, this model emerges from
dynamics of coupling, not from the
neural structure. So coupling, I I don't
know that word. I'm trying to think
about C's, but it's more communicative
communication. I don't know if that's
the right word, but because coupling
again, it's diatic and it's dualistic
and it's two. And when you're on a
bicycle, your constellatory
you know, you're you're coupling with it
lots of things at once. Um, and all of
those things are going into the system
that we're calling that that whatever is
happening in the hippocampus, but also
in all these other ways. I think active
inference obviously already shows this
in a way. There's not prediction errors
living somewhere. they're, you know, in
the dynamics of the levels. But
yeah, I mean, this is where it gets
really tricky and a lot of people could
get very mad at me when I'm thinking
about these ideas in a big way and then
the actual maths of them or the language
even that we're using right now to
describe them and how those get very
confusing.
Um,
so it's not, and I'm sorry, but I don't
think that it's that the math is in our
brain or that the math is in the meat,
you know, uh, or that the language is in
the brain or in the meat or that any of
this needs to be located in that, but
it's more of that's how that's one more
level of exactly this process, which is
why it's so confusing. So when we're
using language or math, we've we've
we've sort of externalized and created
um a representation externally so that
we can share that and couple together
via this so as to better understand one
another's experience. Uh I go into that
more in the paper in a more precise way.
But
so we still write and talk about models
and representations as being inbrains
and in heads even though we know they're
not. And we're separating what's not
separable so as to understand it but
then we forget that it wasn't separable
and we talk about it as if it was
inside. So this idea of holding paradox
is somehow I mean it hurts a bit to try
to think like this but it's not that I
have a thought and it's in my head and
then I encode it in language and then I
describe it to you in words and then
it's in your head and then you know you
have it and it's your representation. Um
it's not there's not a thought that I'm
giving that any of us are giving to each
other in the same way that in the GPS
system or the whatever we want to talk
about what's happening in the
hippocampus there's not some little
hieroglyph that I could have and just
give to you. So it's more this radical
way of thinking about this um which I
think communit it's communicative even
if it's communicative between you what
you think of as yourself and your body
or or parts of your body.
Still language sort of forces us to go
back to talking about models and
representations and brains. It's really
hard to talk about this. Um,
and
if you look at all the neuroscience
papers, we still talk like this, even
though people a lot of this is common
sense as I discussed in the paper. But
why does it matter? I I think it matters
a lot. Uh, I didn't go on my soap box. I
was going to earlier, but because we're
all sort of talking past each other in
ways and I feel like we're getting a
little bit caught up on, especially at
least theoretically, um, on things that
are exciting to argue about, but aren't
actually helping us understand
how to communicate better, how to uh,
understand what's hurting us and others,
um, how to care about that in a deeper
Okay. And I really think so many people
are doing so much amazing work in all
these different fields and then we end
up trying to prove to each other that
our theories are right when we're kind
of saying the same thing just with
different language. So
I know that's a little uh emotional, but
I do think all of this actually really
matters because a lot of the ways we're
just coming at things are are blocked.
We're not seeing the resonance
due due to this. So,
this would be probably too much to go
into. Do I have like five minutes or
something now?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um
I I I I guess if we understood models as
communicative or I was trying to find
some kind of active inference language,
but uh then
it's not that the math has to change or
anything really has to change. what
changes is just our way of talking about
it. And that is hard. A lot of people
who I've talked to this about say that
they know these things. Like it's not
that they're looking for models and
brains, but that they can't help but
talk about it in that way. So
I I wonder how we can sort of shift that
to thinking of this communicative
relational model in a way that would be
easier to discuss, you know, in our
language. Um
yeah I I I don't know. Uh so I was
thinking about language of course
because that's a very fascinating
subject but I was thinking about like
language coordinates as mutual
prediction or we're not transferring
information but we're sort of
scaffolding each other's paths of
communication in that conceptual space
when we're having a conversation. And
language is a set of regularities that
we're sharing in that third way that I
sort of expressed that helps us do that.
So it's like sharing it's it's it's
another kind of landscape that we've
built that we're sharing and that is
conceptual. So if we can start thinking
in these dimensions which is you know
kind of fractal and wild instead of just
it's mental or it's physical we can
start realizing gosh there's so many
landscapes we have to re realize which
ones we're discussing what regularities
we're discussing and how we're sort of
scaffolding one another's way of
entering those landscapes because often
I feel like we're on the edge of some
sort of breakthrough in a lot of our
work but we're not letting the data
resonate because we're not realizing
that we're scaffolding each other out of
each other's um landscape somehow.
Uh yeah, so how could we sort of
coordinate those tra trajectories and
think about it that way? It's just kind
of a wild way to think about it. Last
thing is like giving directions. So when
you give directions, you're you're not
transmitting a representation. you know,
I'm not giving you like my cognitive
map, but you are sort of um co-
scaffolding, you're helping someone else
scaffold what you've already
experienced. So, in a way, you are
sharing away, you're helping scaffold
their their regularities. Um,
yeah. And I think I will leave these
these ideas
for another time. But
I was thinking about reshaping attractor
landscapes as you know in language.
There would be a lot to go in into that.
But
it's just exploration, thinking of it in
this way, trying to get a little bit
almost psychedelic in the sense of
getting out of traditional ways of
thinking about space and get in so doing
realizing we already have a whole lot of
similarities across a lot of different
traditions when it comes to trying to
understand cognition. And that that's
actually very connected to the ways we
move through space already. and that
this might be one way that we can start
to think about
some of this.
Um,
yeah, that's just thinking about what we
mean by space and landscape differently.
And I had a baby example, but and then
this constellatory thing. I don't know
if it makes sense to anyone. So far,
people aren't really sure what the heck
I'm talking about, but I'm kind of
envisioning instead of this either or
diad that we try to understand things
more constellatory. And of course, it
depends on where you're going to center
that, but you know, there's const
constellations and constellations and
constellations. And a lot of systems
theory and of course, graph theory and
everything else is doing a lot of that.
But I I still try to find a way to
envision that and think about it and
maybe language or communication like
understanding that these are different
ways of communicating in different
spaces between different parts of us,
our bodies or different bodies. Um feels
like to me something to maybe explore uh
this constellation of organism,
environment, tools, culture, etc., etc.
And I was thinking of jazz as a kind of
a great example of that as always you
know typical example but just to bring
in some music for the end that this is
uh you know we all bring in our
instruments our language and we create
something in real time coordination that
is for me a kind of constellation a
sensory constellation of all the people
and the ways they're experiencing it and
of that room in that moment. So
yeah,
consolatory, I guess, is the way to
leave it
for now.
Yeah. Okay, I'll just leave it there for
now. I think that's probably the end of
my time and I have to go around 8. But
maybe that made no sense at all, but at
least I tried to put some ideas
together.
So, thanks. You you you put many you put
many stars in the constellation.
Um
>> that's all I need to do. That's all I
wanted to do.
>> There's a lot to reflect in there.
Um
>> indeed
>> I was struck with the
laterality of wayfinding and how that
sort of branch swinging or movement in
the cognitive or material spaces.
It has a sort of flatness which alludes
to the without hierarchies from your
title and a and actuality like whatever
association a given cognitive entity
makes in a moment no matter how comical
or useful or absurd or taboo in a given
situation the association is always
actual.
Whereas when
things are thought of in terms of the
induction and deduction
or there
the jump is from some phenomena to
either a component or to a a a category
or a type of thing,
then it gives a different grip on it.
And so there's sort of a
and and and then you
turn that knot over in your work and in
this presentation from many sides
with what language can and cannot do and
what it what it what it enforces, what
it enables.
And that goes from the whole worldview
scale, the kind of paradigmatic within
professional science and also within
what's more broadly received all the way
down to the very syntactic like between
is diatic but among is three or more or
in is an enclosure preposition but with
is an instrumental.
So it really does make the last mile in
in our utterances
and in in how
our inner and outer landscapes are are
conceptualized of and navigated
which is everything.
>> Yeah. And it has that historical I mean
when you were talking I was thinking of
that the links of it everything we've
been exposed to in those terms you just
expressed before the moment um will be
part of that moment and differently for
each person or each
you know each whatever whatever group or
person might be in question.
I guess the the the
question that I wonder if you have any
insight about is uh
how do we start to think about uh the
space of language as something where
I don't know it's almost like a meta
communicative that we're we don't um
I mean even when when you were just
describing the diatic or the way that we
use language and so on. How do we think
about that as
as its own landscape uh even as we're in
that landscape? Does that make any sense
at all? Is it is it too much to kind of
does it even is it even helpful to be
aware of it like that on a mathematical
level or on a scientific level or
because you know there's been this
debate in neuroscience about like we use
words from William James that we just
sort of look for in the brain. Buzzaki
brought it up and stuff and a lot of
people have debated that of just do we
need new words and so on and uh I wonder
if anyone in the active inference world
that you've talked to or that comes to
mind has had any
insight about
because these are kind of new ways of
talking that that are coming into the
into into the science and yeah I wonder
if that's helpful or that's if if you've
you know if you have anything that comes
to mind when I just even bring that up
actually?
>> Yes. A few few
>> pieces. One is the know that and know
how and other sorts of distinctions that
have been made in cognitive and
linguistic philosophy
>> like the more phenomenological side of
it or you
>> um like propositional knowledge and
different ways of knowing. So
>> Mhm.
giving a structural
framework to help get handles or
or context on what kinds of things can
be expressed through language, what what
kinds of things are are embodied,
skillful performance. Um even uh earlier
today Robert Warden presenting on a sort
of architectural approach which Elliot
Murphy other other people have sort of
laid out pieces where there's a primary
ingress layer from the phonemes in heard
speech or edge detection visual aspects
of reading kind of a primary ingress
into a more concept ceptual
basian graph structured hierarchical
generative model like when you said that
the language models and the world models
are not different and then rather than a
sort of unopinionated
large generic architecture
transformer-based or neural network
based where a given input has a given
embedding or
state space representation and then that
state-based representation can be used
to go like from words to words or from
words to images and things like that.
All the kinds of AI that we see rather
than having that hyperparameterized
unopinionated architecture.
What biological systems with their
sparcity conditions seem to do and what
points towards alternative more
cybernetically informed architectures
would be the structure of that state
space
is somewhere between that generic
and a very very opinionated
very sparse much smaller state space
where samples could be pulled or
representations could exist in that
state space in a moment which could be
used to propagate back out towards
language through introspection or or
self-report or that state space
representation could be used. So so that
would be language emissions or action
planning. So, it's like if I have
situational awareness of the cup to my
right,
I could
perhaps implicitly or explicitly explore
what would happen if I moved it here and
verbally describe that happening
both coming from a common
representation. And then I think what
you are importantly bringing the
empirical papers and and work to the for
is okay GPS is a metaphor. We can go
down that rabbit hole with what
metaphors are but it isn't a static
aloscentric overlay. If we're going to
get into that firsterson
way making and wayfinding, then there's
simultaneously like an egocentric
reference frame and then a sort of
counterfactual ego centric. What would I
see if I were there?
and how that plus
heristics, habits, ways
can address problems that otherwise
would be approached from more of a brute
force
calculative way.
But like seeking higher ground and
looking around
could be a heristic on a landscape
that doesn't go through the policy roll
out of every single location to go to
and what would I expect to see at every
location
that might be solving a problem
in an exhaustive way
where the first person perspective and
heristics give an alternative approach.
But that first person heristic, it's not
doing those rollouts. So it doesn't have
access. So then then that's part of this
kind of disciplinary approach crossfire
where then we're seeking those policy
rollouts in neural data,
but they aren't necessarily even there
because that's reifying what the models
in, you know, the what the what the
program's
>> architectural opinionation is.
>> Yeah. what you're looking for too or
what manifold
comes. But I I have to like curled up in
all that you said
to me. I feel like we confuse like the
the the LLM and the AI side of all this
is so important, right? And but but in a
way we don't understand that those are
not like those are that's a different
velvevelt is what I guess I'm saying
like if we could understand these as
different layers. We have this language
sort of envel or this conceptual space
that we now share in a really profound
way with machines but that's one layer
you know and instead of like saying okay
that's mental and so everything that
we've ever talked about is mental now is
attached to this technology
it's just like I'm trying to kind of you
know manifold this out or separate layer
this out so that we understand we're
study we're sharing a conceptual
dimension now a language based dimension
that's really profound but it's one
dimension um that already maybe def
depends on certain affordances uh that
we're bringing to it. So when you're
talking about that phenomenological
horistic or that that moment, that's why
I really love trying to go back to the
movement itself. And of course we could
talk about robotics and all that we've
learned from movement in robotics about
you know technology and AI but if we
just think about if we if we stop
thinking of it as trying to fit it into
categories and we think of it as a
continuous process without beginnings or
ends and by that I mean whatever we're
studying as cognition
then we start to understand how whatever
position from the moment it is a
position when you're assessing it as
it's moving through whatever
regularities you're defining as the
landscape is building something like
these patterns which we can study in all
these different ways and which are
constillatory or I don't know like
kaleidoscopic or they're sort of layered
in these fractal ways that are really
hard for us to get a grasp on. So like
we we definitely are sharing some um
with technology in a new way right now
based on language but I feel like so
much of that is just getting like you
know we're just taking on all this other
stuff that isn't actually part of that
you know in terms of everything we think
of as what mind and cognition is from a
human point of view. Does that make any
sense at all? Um, it's part of why I'm
trying to find a way to separate out
those things a bit.
>> What kinds of experiments or inquiries
if you had a infinite lab or kind of a
dream setup? What would you want to see?
What kinds of measurements or
experiences or or setups do you think
would would help move beyond
checking for new neuroscience papers and
unifying them within cognitive
frameworks.
I think if we could get away from the
stimulus response
kind of set up in some way, there's
some, you know, I mean that for me is
already based in this uh dualistic
dichomous language that's in a way
that's very hard to get away from where
we the way we approach it already where
there's a subject and there's someone
looking. Maybe one way to do it is to
kind of some find some way to think
about the space that we're in as the
third part of that. and that that we
have to somehow um in our experiments
metrosize the space, the regularities,
the landscape, whether it's the room or
whether it's language if we're doing it
conceptually, if it's a conceptual
experiment or something that I think
there needs to be instead of the
stimulus response, there needs to be
some at least start with a third um the
third as a way into kind of this
constellatory and whether that means
metricizing or thinking about the space
itself, which is already kind of getting
into some ecological experiments. Um, I
would
I would I would have a lot of ideas
about how to start to do that. The
problem is my math skills and my I mean
I can code and stuff, but like really
coming up with different ways of
visualizing this. Um, I mean, I've I've
kind of desperately tried to reach out
to because I think the first step is
more how do we visualize it? All of our
visuals right now are still very hard to
um like express uh that there could be
so many different shared dimensions. How
would we how would we I mean I'm
thinking of graph theory or something or
these other ways that you know even just
small worlds theory and the way we've
tried to visualize things like that but
it would have to be sort of
multi-dimensional where you could
literally sort of somehow feel as if you
can uh visually express how you Daniel
for example are part of many different
um landscapes all the time and your
body's reacting ing to that in in one
continuous way, but when you're going to
study it, you would break it down into
different regularities so so you can
understand it. So what would be the the
world that you're sharing
linguistically?
Um what are those regularities when
you're talking with your family, when
you're talking with a chatbot or
whatever? Um what is that space? How
would you measize that space in a way
that could give you some data so you
could see what the differences are? Um,
how would we even I mean this is a
really crazy idea but you said
unlimited. How would we sort of
blockchain? I mean, how would we
understand like if we took we already do
it in a way with Google and looking at
words and how often they're searched or
something, but how would we like create
these kind of trajectories for, you
know, patterns of language and how, you
know, because right now we use chat bots
and and they're basically pulling on
everything that's ever been said or
written by everyone, you know, that's
online. But how could we follow those
trajectories of where that's coming from
and how that iterated into this, you
know, things like that? I just I feel
like it it's possible now with
technology, but way beyond my
my skill set for for how to kind of do
that. But somehow combining that that
that way of understanding
the different landscapes we're in and
their trajectories into, you know, how
they've evolved to that point and
understanding how we how we are in them
multiple ways at once, which again is
all just a model. It's not the actual
ongoing reality because that's not,
you know, we don't you I'm not saying we
could ever I don't think we could ever
have a twin of that necessarily in the
models, but maybe
I
I hear you on that. It feels like so
many of the pieces are coming together
with agentic approaches to
representation and the way that those
kinds of
small scale operations
in their toy
form all the way up on through extremely
impressive are are being increasingly
described which gives like an
operational grammar for that
process-based ontology.
So programming as as orchestration and
even implicit within object orientation
are transformations and changes to
objects. So again recapitulating a sort
of noun and verb
nons superiority. They play
complimentary parts in in system
expression
and
dealing with those first principles with
those radical aspects of situationality
like whether it's 4E or just perspect
perspectives
all those kinds of features that seem to
fall out at the same time
of that not of engagement
and
the dawning of of systems that let us
describe then see that happen in warp
speed
rather than just imagining it play out
or or doing it manually.
you you sort of do it a bit with the
ants paper the last
>> I can't remember the name of it but
there's some resonance there I think in
what you were
>> what you were doing but I don't remember
the name of it now but
>> in the inferance paper the one of the
pieces that we explored there was just
collective behavior with stigm with the
niche modification
otherwise there's the the landscape of
collective behavior is entirely
transient
like the and and it doesn't leave a
trace. But then
>> if you have
multiscale activity within a space that
is also changing like people are
emitting words into text corpuses that
change the frequencies then it's more
like the the balls are rolling on a
trampoline and they have their own
directions and they're changing the the
space as they move through it. H
>> well, what what
should we be on the lookout for or just
what would be exciting in this last bit
of this year? How do we how do we bring
how do we bring something timely
and contemporary to to a lot of these
questions?
>> Yeah, I guess bring it into our everyday
life wherever we are. you know, how can
we
whatever we're working on
try to notice if we're thinking of it in
um traditionally either or terms um
which we probably are cuz I think most
of us are sort of set up to do that and
most of our systems are set up on that
and maybe letting ourselves dream a
little bit of what might be possible if
we introduced a third or a fourth
uh way of
you know perceiving that. I mean, I
think Johari windows and the fourth in a
lot of different um traditions and the
third, of course, there's so many ways
we've been trying to do this, but
I really feel like a lot of it's going
to be practicing kind of everyday life
uh in noticing that we are still seeing
things in a very particular
orientation and that that's not wrong,
but maybe we could open up our
sensuality.
uh even as scientists or as philosophers
or whatever we are even if you know we
work whatever we're doing uh I find that
like a really rich
way of staying grounded in these times
and of remembering there's a lot of
possibilities and that we can open like
new worlds can open that we didn't
expect uh just through perceptual
shifts.
I don't know if ants have that happen to
them, but I would imagine that they do.
>> Where that takes me is remember and
dream.
>> Remember and dream. Yes. At once.
Sometimes it's the same thing. I mean,
memory and imagination. That's part of I
didn't get into it, but that's actually
part of what you start to see. They're
very, very similar. So, yeah, remember
and dream. That's very good. Let's let's
let's leave it at that. Well, thank you
for always bringing to our space and
institute so much scientific and poetic
and
fun fun videos and writings to always
enjoy.
>> Thank you too, Daniel. I love your work.
You know that I really appreciate you.
Thanks for letting me go a little wild
on this one. It was fun.
>> See you. Thank you.
>> See you. Bye.
That was fun. Thanks.
It's rough right now. Yeah.